A Finding Aid to the Robert Smithson and Nancy Holt Papers, 1905-1987, bulk 1952-1987, in the Archives of American Art AAA.smitrobe
Archives of American Art
Robert Smithson and Nancy Holt papers
bulk 1952-1987
1905-1987
AAA.smitrobe
Archives of American Art
14.9 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor, writer, and earthworks artist Robert Smithson and his wife, sculptor, filmmaker, and earthworks artist Nancy Holt measure 14.9 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1987, with the bulk of the material dating from 1952 to 1987. The papers consist of Smithson's biographical material; business and personal correspondence, much of it with artists; interview transcripts; extensive writings and project files; financial records; printed material; a scrapbook of clippings; holiday cards with original prints and sketches; photographic material; and artifacts. Also found are project files related to Nancy Holt's films Pine Barrens and Suntunnels.
Smithson, Robert
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Robert Smithson and Nancy Holt were donated by Nancy Holt in several accretions between 1986 and 2011.
Separated Material
Motion picture films transferred to videocassette, non-archival library books, periodicals, and phonographs from Robert Smithson's personal library are currently stored offsite.
Related Material
The Archives also holds several collections related to Robert Smithson and Nancy Holt, including an oral history interview with Robert Smithson conducted by Paul Cummings in 1972; an interview with Robert Smithson conducted by Tony Robbin in 1968; Robert Smithson letters to George B. Lester, 1960-1963; and oral history interviews with Nancy Holt conducted by Scott Gutterman in 1992 and Joyce Pomeroy Schwartz in 1993.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Robert Smithson (1938-1973) was the pioneer of land and earthworks art. He was also a noted sculptor, painter, writer, and lecturer working primarily in New York City. Smithson's wife, Nancy Holt (1938-) was a noted sculptor and filmmaker and also worked as an earthworks artist.
Born in Passaic, New Jersey, Smithson expressed an early interest in art, enrolling in classes at the Brooklyn Museum School and the Art Student's League in New York while still attending high school. Smithson's early works were primarily paintings, drawings, and collages. In 1959, he exhibited his first solo show of paintings at the Artists' Gallery in New York and had his first solo international show in Rome with the Galleria George Lester in 1961.
During the early to mid-1960s, Smithson was perhaps better known as a writer and art critic, writing numerous essays and reviews for Arts Magazine and Artforum. He became affiliated with artists who were identified with the minimalist movement, such as Carl Andre, Donald Judd, Nancy Holt, Sol LeWitt, Robert Morris and others. In 1963, Smithson married sculptor and filmmaker Nancy Holt and a year later started to create his first sculptural works. In 1966, Smithson joined the Dwan Gallery, whose owner Virginia Dwan was an enthusiastic supporter of his work.
Smithson's interest in land art began in the late 1960s while exploring industrial and quarry sites and observing the movement of earth and rocks. This resulted in a series of sculptures called "non-sites" consisting of earth and rocks collected from a specific site and installed in gallery space, often combined with photographs, maps, mirrors, or found materials. In September 1968, Smithson published the essay "A Sedimentation of the Mind: Earth Projects" in Artforum that promoted the work of the first wave of land art artists. Soon thereafter, he began creating his own large scale land art and earthworks.
From 1967 to 1973, Smithson's productivity was constant as he wrote, lectured, and participated in several solo and group shows a year, both at home and abroad. He explored narrative art as essay in "The Monuments of Passaic" and fully committed to his idea of visiting sites and using them as the basis for creating non-sites, Non-Site, Pine Barrens, (1968); incorporated and documented the use of mirrors at sites in Mirror Displacement, Cayuga Salt Mine Project (1968-1969); and created his first site-specific works through liquid pours of mud, asphalt, and concrete, including Asphalt Rundown (1969). In 1969, he also completed his first earth pour at Kent State University with his project Partially Buried Woodshed. Later that year, he created the sculptural artwork for which he is best known, Spiral Jetty (1969) on the Great Salt Lake in Utah. This was the first of his pieces to require the acquisition of land rights and earthmoving equipment, and would be followed two years later by Broken Circle and Spiral Hill in 1971.
On July 20, 1973, while surveying sites in Texas for the proposed Amarillo Ramp, Smithson died in a plane crash at the age of 35. Despite his early death, Smithson's writings and artwork had a major impact on many contemporary artists.
Nancy Holt began her career as a photographer and video artist. Today, Holt is most widely known for her large-scale environmental works, Sun Tunnels and Dark Star Park. Holt has also made a number of films and videos since the late 1960s, including Mono Lake (1968), East Coast, West Coast (1969), and Swamp (1971) in collaboration with her late husband Robert Smithson. Points of View: Clocktower (1974) features conversations between Lucy Lippard and Richard Serra, Liza Bear and Klaus Kertess, Carl Andre and Ruth Kligman and Bruce Brice and Tina Girouard. In 1978, she produced a film about her seminal work Sun Tunnels.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of sculptor, writer, and earthworks artist Robert Smithson and his wife, sculptor, filmmaker, and earthworks artist Nancy Holt measure 14.9 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1987, with the bulk of the material dating from 1952 to 1987. The papers consist of Smithson's biographical material; business and personal correspondence, much of it with artists; interview transcripts; extensive writings and project files; financial records; printed material; a scrapbook of clippings; holiday cards with original prints and sketches; photographic material; and artifacts. Also found are project files related to Nancy Holt's films Pine Barrens and Suntunnels.
Biographical material includes Robert Smithson's curriculum vitae, personal identification and medical documents, eight engagement/day planners Smithson and Holt maintained from 1966 to 1973, and Smithson's funeral register.
Correspondence is primarily with Smithson's family, friends, fellow artists, and business associates discussing personal relationships, proposed art projects, and exhibitions. Correspondents of note include Carl Andre, the Dwan Gallery (Virginia Dwan), Dan Graham, Will Insley, Ray Johnson, Gyorgy Kepes, Sol Lewitt, Lucy Lippard, and Dennis Wheeler. There is also substantial correspondence received by Holt upon Smithson's death in 1973, and between Holt and the Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art regarding Smithson's retrospective exhibition in 1982.
There are nine interview transcripts with Smithson discussing his works and his general philosophy on art, and one transcript of the Andrew Dickson White Museum's Earth Art Symposium (1969) featuring the following artists: Mike Hiezer, Dennis Oppenheim, Robert Smithson, Neil Jenney, Gunther Uecker, Jan Dibbets, Richard Long, and Hans Haacke.
Writings are substantial and include 73 drafts of published and unpublished essays by Smithson on art, artists, and works in progress. The series also includes poems by Smithson, six notebooks containing notes and sketches by Smithson, and drafts of writings sent to Smithson and Holt by friends and colleagues, including Carl Andre, Terry Atkinson, Dan Flavin, Dan Graham, and Jack Thibeau.
Project files contain correspondence, project instructions, diagrams and sketches, research materials, photographic material, and maps related to over 50 of Smithson's artworks. These include concepts, proposed projects, sculptures, non-sites, and earthwork projects, including Spiral Jetty, Broken Circle, and Spiral Hill.
Personal business records include gallery related loan arrangements and receipts for miscellaneous art supplies. Financial records include tax forms and preparation documents, including cancelled checks, receipts, statements, and related correspondence.
Printed materials include books, clippings, and periodicals related to Smithson, either containing writings or sketches by him, or containing articles reviewing his work. There are also exhibition announcements and catalogs of Smithson's group and solo shows from 1959 to 1985.
The scrapbook contains clippings of Smithson's published articles from 1966 to 1973 with annotated shorthand notes.
Artwork consists of Christmas cards collaged by Smithson, and sketches by Smithson and Leo Valledor.
Photographic materials include prints and negatives of Smithson with friends, promotional Hollywood movie stills, and original prints and copyprints of other artists' artwork.
Artifacts consist of a paper bag silkscreened with a Campbell's soup can (Warhol), promotional buttons (N.E. Thing Co.), various organic materials, and two art kits.
Nancy Holt's papers consist of correspondence, a grant application, printed materials, and project files and audio visual material related to her motion picture films Pine Barrens (1975) and Suntunnels (1975).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 13 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1905-1974 (Box 1; 14 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1959-1987 (Boxes 1-2, OV 21; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Interview Transcripts, 1966-1973 (Box 2; 11 folders)
Series 4: Writings, 1959-1975 (Boxes 2-3; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 5: Project Files, circa 1950s-1982 (Boxes 4-5, Boxes 17-18, OV 20, OV 22-26, OV 36, RD 28-30, RD 32-35; 6.5 linear feet)
Series 6: Personal Business Records, circa 1967-1970s (Box 5; 4 folders)
Series 7: Financial Records, 1962-1972 (Box 6; 1 linear foot)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1955-1985 (Boxes 7-11, Box 18, RD 31; 5.6 linear feet)
Series 9: Scrapbook, 1966-1973 (Box 11, Box 16; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 10: Artwork, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 11; 4 folders)
Series 11: Photographs, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 11, Box 18; 5 folders)
Series 12: Artifacts, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 11, Box 14, OV 19; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 13: Nancy Holt Papers, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 12-13, Box 15, OV 27; 1.7 linear feet)
Andre, Carl, 1935-; Atkinson, Terry, 1939-; Dibbets, Jan, 1941-; Dwan Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Dwan, Virginia; Flavin, Dan, 1933-; Graham, Dan, 1942-; Haacke, Hans, 1936-; Heizer, Michael, 1944-; Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art; Holt, Nancy, 1938-; Insley, Will, 1929-2011; Jenney, Neil, 1945-; Johnson, Ray, 1927-; Kepes, Gyorgy, 1906-2001; LeWitt, Sol, 1928-2007; Lippard, Lucy R.; Long, Richard, 1945-; Oppenheim, Dennis, 1938-2011; Valledor, Leo; Wheeler, Dennis; Art -- Philosophy; Authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Earthworks (Art); Filmmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Greeting cards; Interviews; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Sketches; Transcripts
- Biographical Materials, 1905-1974; Series 1; 14 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The series consists of Smithson's curriculum vitae, a list of favorite things, an Art Students League class evaluation, vaccination records, a passport, a wallet, and eight engagement/day planners Smithson and Holt maintained from 1966 to 1973. Miscellaneous materials include an article on Charles Smithson and a photocopy of the front page of the New York Herald Tribune on the day of Robert Smithson's birth. The series also includes a funeral register and an artist's statement prepared by three unidentified friends upon Smithson's death.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List, "My Favorites,", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Students League Class Evaluation, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Passport and Vaccination Records, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wallet, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1966-1973; 6 Folders (Box 1, Folder 6-11)
  - Artists' Statement Following Smithson's Death, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Funeral Register and Cards, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1905-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1959-1987; Series 2; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 21
  Correspondence is primarily with Smithson's family, friends, fellow artists, and business associates discussing personal relationships, proposed art projects, and exhibitions.
  The series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  2.1: Family, 1959-1987
  2.2: General, 1961-1984
  2.3: Condolences, 1973
  - Family, 1959-1987; 2.1
    Family correspondence consists of letters from Smithson to Nancy Holt and postcards from Smithson and Holt to Smithson's parents, Susan and Irving. Smithson's postcards to his parents detail his travels to Europe and updates on life and work projects in the 1960s-1970s. Holt's postcards describe her travel and projects in the 1970s-1980s.
    - Holt, Nancy, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Smithson, Susan and Irving, 1959-1987; 3 Folders (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - General, 1961-1984; 2.2
    General correspondence includes a handful of letters drafted by Smithson and Holt, with the bulk of the subseries comprising of letters from artists, art critics, collectors, museums, galleries, art organizations, universities, real estate brokers, and businesses.
    There is correspondence of note from the Dwan Gallery (Virginia Dwan) and from artist friends Carl Andre, Dan Flavin, Konrad Fischer, Dan Graham, Peter Hutchinson, Will Insley, Ray Johnson, Gyorgy Kepes, Sol Lewitt, Lucy Lippard, Toby Mussman, Claes Oldenburg, Dennis Oppenheim, Robert Wade, and Dennis Wheeler. There is also substatial correspondence between Holt and Robert Hobbs regarding the Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art's retrospective Smithson exhibition in 1982.
    - A, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Includes letters from Vito Acconci
    - ACE Gallery, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Andre, Carl, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Art International, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Art News, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Artforum (Leider, Phil), 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - B, Miscellaneous, 1963-1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes letters from Jo Baer, John Baldessari, Bernd and Hilla Becher, and Donald Burgy
    - C, Miscellaneous, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Includes letters from Ted Castle, Rosemarie Castoro, Ron Cooper, and Bill Copley
    - Celant, Germano, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Centro de Arte y Comunicacion, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Columbia University, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - D, Miscellaneous, 1963-1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Includes letters from Jan Dibbets, Herbert Distel, Peter Downsbrough, and Thomas Downing
    - Dwan Gallery (Dwan, Virginia), 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - E-F, Miscellaneous, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Includes letters from Hamish Fulton
    - Fischer, Candace, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Fischer, Konrad, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Flavin, Dan, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - G, Miscellaneous, 1961-1972 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Gemeentemuseum (Develing, Enno), 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - George Braziller, Inc., 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Graham, Dan, circa 1960s; 2 Folders (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
    - Guggenheim Museum, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - H, Miscellaneous, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Includes letters from Hans Haacke, Tim Head, Doug Huebler, and Sam Hunter
    - Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, Cornell University (Hobbs, Robert C.), 1979-1984; 5 Folders (Box 1, Folder 43-47)
    - Hutchinson, Peter, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - I, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Includes letter from Robert Indiana
    - Insley, Will, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - J, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Johnson, Ray, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Junker, Howard, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - K, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes letters from Wolf Kahlen, Halasz Karoly, Kasper Konig, Bruce Kurtz, and Joseph Kosuth
    - Kepes, Gyorgy, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Kurtz, Bruce, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - L, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Includes letters from Lallie Lloyd and Lee Lozano
    - Lewitt, Sol, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lippard, Lucy, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Long, Richard, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - M, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Includes letters from Joe Masheck and Robert Morris
    - McConathy, Dale, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Moderna Museet, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Museum of Modern Art, 1961-1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Mussman, Toby, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - N, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - N.E. Thing Co., 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - New York State Council on the Arts (Hunter, Sam), 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Nova Scotia School of Art, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - O-P, Miscellaneous, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Includes letters from John Perreault and Larry Poons
    - Oldenburg, Claes, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Oppenheim, Dennis, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - R, Miscellaneous, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Includes letters from Ed Ruscha
    - Real Estate Related, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Oversized material housed in OV 21
    - Rhode Island School of Design, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Robbin, Anthony, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - S, Miscellaneous, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Includes letters from Harry Soviak, Petr Stembera, and Marjorie Strider
    - Sao Paulo Bienal (Kepes, Gyorgy), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Sharp, Willoughby, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Smithson, Robert, 1961-1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Sonsbeek, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - T, Miscellaneous, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Includes letters from Paul Thek
    - Ta' (Berg, H.M.), 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - U, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - University of Utah, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - V, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Includes letters from Jan van der Marck
    - Vollmer, Ruth, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - W, Miscellaneous, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Includes letter from Mac Wells
    - Walker Art Center, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Wheeler, Dennis, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Y, Miscellaneous, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Yale University, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Unidentified and Illegible, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Condolences, 1973; 2.3
    Condolences consists of letters, cards, and notes of sympathy from family and friends addressed to Nancy Holt upon the death of Smithson.
    - A-C, Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - D-H, Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - I-M, Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - N-R, Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - S-Z, Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Real Estate Related, 1968-1972 (Box OV 21)
      Oversized material from Box 2, F21
- Interview Transcripts, 1966-1973; Series 3; 11 Folders Box 2
  This series includes nine interview transcripts with Robert Smithson. Topics include his general philosophy on art; contemporary art in relation to its historical context; non-sites, earthworks, entropy, space, and structures; the relationship between artists and dealers, museums, and collectors; and his most influential works, including Spiral Jetty, Broken Circle, and Spiral Hill.
  The Alan Kaprow and Rodger Katan transcript (1966) focuses on the relationship between museums and contemporary art. The transcript with Dennis Wheeler (1969-1970) consists of 4 taped, informal sessions discussing Smithson's general philosophy on art, non-sites, and specific projects. In the Paul Toner transcript (1970), Smithson discusses earthworks, mirror displacements, non-sites, and art's historical context. The Gregorie Muller transcript [1971] focuses on the background and construction of Broken Circle and Spiral Hill. The Art Institute of Chicago transcript (1971) records Smithson's question and answer session with the audience after a showing of his videos Swamp and Spiral Jetty. In the Bruce Kurtz transcript (1972), Smithson informally discusses artists' relationships with dealers, museums, and collectors; gallery art's general separation from nature; capitalism's influence and intersection with art; and his 1966 airport projects.
  The Stella Russell (1973) transcript focuses on Spiral Jetty, Broken Circle, and Spiral Hill. In the Alison Sky transcript (1973), Smithson discusses his thoughts on entropy, the act of building, and its intersection with the architectural and engineering mechanics of structure. In Smithson's transcript with two unidentified students (1973), he discusses modernism and the branching off of developing contemporary art; public sculpture; historical context, theory, linguistics, and humanism; and thoughts on his own writings. The transcript with Moira Roth (1973) focuses on Duchamp and conceptual art.
  There is also a full transcript of the Andrew Dickson White Museum's Earth Art Symposium (1969) with the following participating artists: Mike Hiezer, Dennis Oppenheim, Robert Smithson, Neil Jenney, Gunther Uecker, Jan Dibbets, Richard Long, and Hans Haacke.
  This series is arranged in chronological order by year of the interview.
  - Robert Smithson and Rodger Katan with Alan Kaprow, "What is a Museum? Notes of Meeting on Museums,", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Transcript of Earth Art Symposium, Cornell University, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Robert Smithson with Dennis Wheeler, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Robert Smithson with Paul Toner, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Robert Smithson with Gregoire Miller, circa 1971 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Robert Smithson at the Art Institute of Chicago, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Robert Smithson with Bruce Kurtz, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Robert Smithson with Stella Russell, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Robert Smithson with Alison Sky, "Entropy Made Visible,", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Robert Smithson with Two Students, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Robert Smithson with Moira Roth, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Writings, 1959-1975; Series 4; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Writings consist of drafts of published and unpublished essays by Smithson on art, artists, and works in progress. The series also includes poems by Smithson, six notebooks containing notes and sketches by Smithson, and drafts of writings sent to Smithson and Holt by friends and colleagues, including Carl Andre, Terry Atkinson, Dan Flavin, and Dan Graham.
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  4.1: By Robert Smithson, circa 1959-1973
  4.2: By Others, 1962-1975
  - By Robert Smithson, circa 1959-1973; 4.1